DeSole, Gloria; Papers apap215
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gloria DeSole Papers
1969-1988
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap215
2.0 cubic ft.
The collection pertains to the Women's movement during the 1960s-1980s, with an emphasis on LGBTQ+ women. Other subjects of interest include the experiences of working and professional women, and women who either worked in, or attended institutions of higher education. Many items in the collection are focused on women in the Capital Region of New York State.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2004, 2021, 2024 and 2025 by Gloria DeSole and Meredith Butler.
Biographical History
Born in 1937, Gloria DeSole is a former employee of the University at Albany, having served as the senior adviser to the President for Affirmative Action and Employment Planning and Director of Affirmative Action from 1982 to 2000. Before DeSole's retirement, she was awarded the President's Undergraduate Leadership Award. During her term of service, DeSole expanded opportunities for women and minority faculty, staff and students. Prior to joining SUNY Albany in 1976, DeSole was an English professor at Skidmore College. She obtained her B.A. in 1959, and her Ph.D. in 1969, both from SUNY Albany. She also earned a master's degree from Columbia University. Other awards she has received during her career and dedication to social activism include the University at Albany's President's Lifetime Justice Award, the Citizen Laureate Award, and the Harvey Milk Award for her activism for the LGBTQ+ community.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of materials related to the women's movement, lesbian culture, and the experiences of professional women in the workplace. The bulk of materials are publications of academic and cultural journals. Also included are drafts of speeches created by Gloria DeSole, and notes on local organizations that served women in the Capital District. Also present in the collection is a copy of a master's thesis.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Related Materials
The following collections at the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives are related to the Gloria DeSole Papers: Caucus on Women's Rights at SUNY, Albany Chapter Records, 1970-1976, Joan Schultz Papers, ca. 1968-1980, Judith Fetterley Papers, 1971-1993, National Organization for Women – Albany, N.Y. Chapter Records, 1971-2005, and National Organization for Women (NOW), New York State Chapter Records, 1961-2011. Additional related collections can be found at the subject pages for Women, Human Sexuality and Gender Identity, and Education.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred one monograph, Female Studies X: Learning to Speak, edited by Deborah Silverton Rosenfelt to the book division of Special Collections. It will be catalogued and included in the University Library Catalog.
Women; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Education; Albany, New York; Women's rights--New York (State); Women--Employment--New York (State); Homosexuality--Law and legislation--New York (State); Correspondence; Serials (publications); Speeches (documents); DeSole, Gloria, 1937-
- Academic Women, Sex Discrimination and the Law - MLA Commission on the Status of Women – Modern Language Association, 1975 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Albany Student Press (ASP), Vol. LXV, No. 31, 1978 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Aphra, Vol. 1 No. 1, 1969 Fall (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Aurora, Issue 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Bitch Manifesto, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Capital Area Women, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Capital District Women – Tri-City Women's Center, 1972 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Careers and Couples - An Academic Question, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Change: The Magazine of Higher Learning, 1975 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chrysalis: A Magazine of Women's Culture, No. 1-No. 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chrysalis: A Magazine of Women's Culture, No. 5-No. 7, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chrysalis: A Magazine of Women's Culture, No. 8, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Complaints and Disorders: The Sexual Politics of Sickness, Glass Mountain Pamphlet No. 2, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Conditions: One, A Magazine of Writing by Women with an Emphasis on Writing by Lesbians, 1977 April (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Dyke: A Quarterly, For Womyn Only, 1975-1976 Winter; 1976 Fall; 1976-1977 Winter (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Elizabeth Cady Stanton, The Feminist Press Catalog No. 1, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Esquire, 1973 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Everywoman: Every Woman is Our Sister, Vol. 2, No. 6, 1971 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "Feminism in the Seventies: A Study of the Women's Liberation Movement of Albany, New York, 1969-1979," Margaret Boys, MA Thesis, Goddard College, 1980 August (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Feminist Voice, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hera: A Philadelphia Feminist Publication, 1975 June (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art and Politics, Vol. 1, No. 2, 1977 May (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Index to the First Ten Years, 1972-1982", Women's Studies Quarterly, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Knickerbocker News, Albany, NY, 1970 August (Box 1, Folder 25)
- The Lesbian Feminist, Vol. 1, No. 2, 4, 1973 October; 1974 February-1974 March (Box 1, Folder 26)
- The Lesbian Tide, 1973 September-1973 December (Box 1, Folder 27)
- The Lesbian Tide, 1974 January; 1974 March-1974 April (Box 1, Folder 28)
- The Lesbian Tide, 1974 May-1974 September (Box 1, Folder 29)
- The Liberated Woman's Appointment Calendar and Field Manual, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Majority Report: A Feminist Newspaper Serving the Women of New York, Vol. 3, No. 1, 1973 May (Box 1, Folder 31)
- MLA Newsletter, Vol. 3, No. 1, 1971 February (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Motive, The Lesbian/Feminist Issue, Vol. 32, No. 1, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Moving Out, Vol. 1, No. 1-2, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- National Women's Studies Association (NYWSA), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- New York, Includes a Preview of Ms. Magazine, 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Notes from Barnard College Conference on Special Programs for Women in Higher Education, 1979 March (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Out: The Gay Perspective, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Radical Teacher, No. 4, 6, 11, 1977; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Re Reading, The Center for the Arts and Humanities, The University at Albany, Vol. 1, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- The Second Wave, Vol. 1, No. 1-4, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Second Wave, Vol. 2, No. 1-4, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Second Wave, Vol. 3, No. 1-4, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Second Wave, Vol. 4, No. 1-4, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The Second Wave, Vol. 5, No. 1-3, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Shrew, Vol. 3, No. 2, 5, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Signs Reader: Women, Gender and Scholarship, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Sinister Wisdom, 1978 Fall; 1979 Winter (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Sojourner: The Women's Forum, 1984 October-1984 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Speak Out, 1972 January; 1972 May-1972 June; 1972 September-1972 November (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Speak Out, 1973 February-1973 March; 1973 May-1973 July; 1973 October-1973 December (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Speak Out, 1974 February-1974 March; 1974 June-1974 July; 1974 September; 1974 November (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Speak Out, 1976 July-1976 August; 1977 April (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Speeches and Notes, 1972-1973; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Woman: A Select Bibliography of Books, 1974 January (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Woman's Place in the Workforce: Issues in Industrial Society, Vol. 2, No. 1, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Womankind, Vol. 1, No. 4, 1971 December (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Women: A Journal of Liberation, 1970 Summer (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Women: A Journal of Liberation, 1970 Fall-Winter (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Women: A Journal of Liberation, Vol. 2, No. 3-4; Vol. 3, No. 3; Vol. 5, No. 2, 1971-1972; 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- "Women in the Eighties: Strategies for Solidarity," New York State Women's Conference, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Women: The Longest Revolution, Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Women and Revolution: The Journal of the Women's Commission of the Spartacist League, 1975-1976 Winter (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Women Speaking, 1970 July-1970 September (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Women's Free Press, 1970 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Women's Studies: An Interdisciplinary Journal, Vol. 1, No. 1, 3, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Women's Studies: An Interdisciplinary Journal, Vol. 2, No. 1, 3, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Women's Studies: An Interdisciplinary Journal, Vol. 3, No. 1, 3, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Women's Studies: An Interdisciplinary Journal, Vol. 4, No. 2/3; Vol. 5, No. 1, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "Unladylike and Unprofessional": Academic Women and Academic Unions MLA (Modern Language Association) Commission on the Status of Women, 1975 January (Box 2, Folder 30)